<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Renormalized]]></title>
  <link href="http://tallguy76.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tallguy76.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-27T17:50:03-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tallguy76.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeffrey Willson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[End of the second week]]></title>
    <link href="http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/end-of-the-second-week/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T17:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/end-of-the-second-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the weekend I spent some time rethinking my typing technique based on David&rsquo;s
advice to remap the Caps Lock key to Control. It&rsquo;s definitely an
improvement. I&rsquo;m also reducing my need for the corners of the keyboard
by using Ctrl-H for Backspace, Ctrl-[ for Escape, Ctrl-J for Return, and
reassigning several keys away from the pinkies. Now 8 and 9 are assigned
to the right middle finger, 0 and &ndash; are on the ring finger, and P is on
the ring finger if it follows anything that uses the right pinky.
Both ring fingers are allowed to cross over the pinkies when the latter
are on the shift keys: Right-shift-(anything) followed by &ldquo;;&rdquo; or &ldquo;&lsquo;&rdquo; get the
ring finger for the second character; Left-shift-(anything) followed by
Ctrl-(anything right hand) gets the ring finger on the Control (formerly
Caps Lock) key. The general principle is not to let either pinky press
different keys on consecutive keystrokes. Command and Option are
assigned to the left thumb; those are the only keys assigned to it.</p>

<p>On Monday and Tuesday we wrote a blackjack-playing program and then got into SQL, working in pairs.
Learning SQL has been going much more smoothly this week than when I tried teaching myself last year.  I went through a group of complex SQL queries, developing fluency in SELECT statements, and have then started thinking about how to organize my Chinese vocabulary lists into a relational database.</p>

<p>Since
Brendan and I finished the Blackjack early, I spent the late morning of Tuesday working on keybinding macros for Sublime Text (so that I can reliably use Esc and Enter regardless of proposed completions popping up).  There are still peculiarities of that editor that I&rsquo;m having a hard time getting used to. For instance, on it like many other editors, Ctrl-H works like backspace. (Early computer terminals established this equivalence: the ASCII code for backspace is 8, the code for H is 72, and the control key of early keyboards caused a code to be sent mod 32. 72 mod 32 = 8.) However, the keys don&rsquo;t work exactly the same in Sublime: the editor doesn&rsquo;t seem to support mapping one key to another, so each key has to be mapped to each function separately. This makes for repetitive default keybinding files that are hard to update consistently, and as a result, there are inconsistencies: when you type a quotation mark, it automatically inserts a pair of them with the cursor in between, and when you then type Backspace, the pair disappears; but when you type Ctrl-H, only the one before the cursor disappears.  The Tab key also has some confusing behavior. It is normally bound to autocomplete words or insert snippets, but inside a Ruby string you can see a word completion, hit tab and get an HTML snippet instead.</p>

<p>Often, David uses Vim as his text editor in class, and Nimit uses TextMate.  I guess they recommended Sublime to us because it is one that both of them find usable, though it apparently has not become either one&rsquo;s favorite.</p>

<p>Wednesday and yesterday we spent time implementing a stripped-down version of ActiveRecord::Base, and then in the afternoon we made short presentations (TTL: &ldquo;Teach to learn&rdquo;) intended to help us gain clarity in our understanding of classes, objects and database tables, and to uncover any misconceptions we may have.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had generally positive with the commute this week; last night I had a pleasant walk to the World Trade Center, and made the connection from the PATH train to the NJTransit with no waiting. That, however was a matter of dumb luck.  Usually, when I come home after rush hour I have to wait a long time for the train and ride a slow local train. The later I stay, the longer my commute on average. Train schedules are encouraging me to leave early.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still working on my typing skill on the side. I&rsquo;ve decided that since I am embarking on the path to be a professional power user of computer keyboards, this is the time to take my typing skills to the next level. Last weekend, as mentioned before, I spent a lot of time practicing the efficient ergonomics of using a control key where the caps lock key normally is; I also spent time reading up on mechanical keyboards (ones with individual mechanical switches for the keys).  Monday night on my way home, I stopped at J&amp;R to get a feel for some. They had keyboards in stock with Cherry MX Blue switches (designed to make an audible click when they register the keystroke) and Cherry MX Red (smooth, no tactile or audible cues for when they&rsquo;ve registered). I found that the touch was
surprisingly light, and that the (useless) noise they make when keystrokes bottom out is much louder than the useful click when the keys register. They didn&rsquo;t have any keyboards with the brown switches (designed to be quiet but to feel like the blue switches.) I went home and ordered a refurbished keyboard with blue switches ($80) and a box of rubber O-rings to put under each key in order to dampen the noises.  Eighty dollars is definitely at the top of the price range that I&rsquo;m willing to pay for a computer keyboard, especially one that is not appropriate for work environments, but it seems to be the bottom end of the current market for mechanical keyboards. I could have bought a new instance of the same keyboard at J&amp;R for $130. The O-rings have not yet arrived, and without them the keyboard is definitely too loud.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week One Summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/week-one-summary/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T21:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/week-one-summary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first week of the Fullstack course has come to a close;
taking the course is making me learn to use tools that I hadn&rsquo;t
gotten around to using before: Git, blogging tools, rspec.
We started the course with a basic exercise in HTML and CSS, building a personal website based on an image. Uploading our solutions to a unified repository became an interesting exercise in the use of Git. After that we reviewed (and completed) basic Ruby exercises from the pre-term assignment, but
the most interesting thing we did in the first week was probably setting up a blog on Octopress.</p>

<p>The recommended
format for composing blogs on Octopress is a simple markup language called Markdown, which is preprocessed into HTML. What&rsquo;s distinctive about Markdown is its simplicity and elegance:
the source file looks almost exactly like plain text and the formatting
commands are unobtrusive, yet it supports the most important
HTML elements to use in structuring text. I&rsquo;ve
used Markdown to reformat the private journal that will form the basis for this blog, and will continue to write in this format.</p>

<p>The
biggest challenge I&rsquo;ve experienced so far has been associated with the commute.
Before the course started I knew how to get to Fullstack by taking New Jersey Transit into Manhattan (Penn Station) and then taking the subway.
Riding New
Jersey Transit is generally pleasant&mdash;I sit down, get out my iPad,
and have time to watch web development tutorials from Team Treehouse.
In the middle of the week, however, I
decided to try the PATH train.  Three days ago I didn&rsquo;t even know
what the PATH train is, but on Tuesday morning I happened to be
looking out the window on the left side of the train when we stopped in Newark
Penn Station (can&rsquo;t they give the stations more distinctive names?);
and I saw that there were turnstiles leading to a light rail train labeled &ldquo;Port
Authority Trans Hudson&rdquo;, heading to the World Trade Center. I&rsquo;d been to New York
before and seen signs to PATH, but none of those signs had informed me that those signs lead to a train line to New Jersey.
It was by looking out the the window that,
absurdly late, I learned that there is a light rail from New
Jersey direct to downtown Manhattan.</p>

<p>That night, to try out the PATH train, I took the
subway to the Park Place stop where the signs and announcements
said &ldquo;connection is available to the PATH train&rdquo;, found the station,
and went down to the tracks.  The monitor there announced, &ldquo;Due to signal
problems, the trains between WTC and Newark in both directions are
subject to a 10 minute delay.&rdquo; I took the train to Newark, got out,
spent several minutes wandering through the train station (those
readers who are familiar with the station already know that this
reflects a serious mistake) until I found the track, just
after missing a train, and waited fifteen minutes for the next train.</p>

<p>Last night I tried the PATH train again. This time I walked to WTC,
and when I got there the monitors said, &ldquo;Due to a sick passenger,
the trains between WTC and Newark in both directions are subject
to a 10 minute delay.&rdquo;  The train I boarded had twenty minutes of
accumulated passengers, and was very full; the next one was already
on the track opposite, and was almost empty. After 25 minutes of being
squeezed like a sardine on that train, I got off and saw a corridor:
To Westbound Connecting Trains. It takes you straight to the platform
that I had taken so long to find two nights before! If I&rsquo;d seen it two nights before, I wouldn&rsquo;t have missed the train.
Getting back to my story, I didn&rsquo;t get on the first train, because it
was heading to Jersey Avenue and I didn&rsquo;t know where that was.
Instead, I waited for the first Northeast Corridor train to Trenton. Once I was on, I discovered I was on the wrong train: it was an express train, next stop Princeton Junction. I watched the train go past New Brunswick, go past Jersey Avenue (oh, that&rsquo;s where it is) and continue on. My wife decided to drive to Princeton to pick me up, and so I spent almost an hour at the station waiting for her. It was four hours after leaving Fullstack that I finally got home.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Renormalized is back to normal for the first time]]></title>
    <link href="http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/renormalized-is-back-to-normal-for-the-first-time/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T12:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tallguy76.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/renormalized-is-back-to-normal-for-the-first-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The initial post of this blog. It will never again be without a post</h2>

<p>Fullstack Academy recommended that start keeping a journal when we
began the prep work. Thus I&rsquo;ve got a wealth of relevant material that I <em>could</em> put online here, but
I&rsquo;m not sure it would be interesting to anybody. Typical excerpt:</p>

<blockquote><p>The CodeAcademy tutorial was slightly annoying. I wonder why it recommends the syntax</p>

<p><code>
var f = function (x){};
</code></p>

<p>defining a lambda and assigning a value to it, instead of
<code>
function f(x){}
</code></p></blockquote>

<p>On request I&rsquo;ve got a <strong>lot</strong> more of this that I could add.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
